A Guide to the Named/Individual Photograph Collections, 1890s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Named/Individual Photograph Collections, 1890s-present
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Photographs.002
4.7 Cubic Feet; 11 boxes; 2 oversize boxes
The Named/Individual Photograph Collections include images from alumni and former faculty and staff, or individuals with ties to campus and the New River Valley. Collections (c.1890-present) depict campus life and events, railroad history, agricultural extension research, Blacksburg and surrounding areas, and some local families.
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Source of Acquisition
Named/Individual Photograph Collections consist primarily of donations to the Special Collections and University Archives over time.
Scope and Content
Each of the Named/Individual Photograph Collections has a description in the "Contents List" below. The majority of the collections, however, are from alumni and former faculty and staff, or individuals with ties to campus and the New River Valley. Collections depict campus life and events, railroad history, agricultural extension research, Blacksburg and surrounding areas, and some local families.
In most cases, collections are named for the collector/creator or based on the subject matter.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by named collection. Each named collection listed has at least one photograph; some subjects have multiple folders or boxes.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Archival Material
Faculty/Staff Photograph Collection
Historical Photograph Collection
Rights Statement for Archival Description
The guide to the Named/Individual Photograph Collections by Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, is licensed under a CC0 (https://creativecommons.org/share-your- work/public-domain/cc0/).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Agricultural extension work; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Photographs; Railroad; University History; Women -- History
Organizations:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. Corps of Cadets
Contents List
- BILLUPS, H. E., Football player and member of 1910 class. Collection includes images of VPI campus, cadets, 1909 sports team; also a photo of the home that served the Thanksgiving meal which coined the term Virginia Tech "Gobblers."
- BLACK FAMILY/KENT FAMILY/APPERSON FAMILY COLLECTIONS:, Ms1974-003; Early Blacksburg families, connected by marriage. Collection includes photographs of Germanicus Kent, Aratus Kent, Dr. Kent Black, and unidentified men standing in Keister's Store in Blacksburg.
- BRAUER, RUDOLPH CARL, Ms1982-011; Class of 1915. Collection consists of forty-five photographs of campus life, 1911-15, and eight photos taken during the Golden Jubilee, 1922.
- BURCHARD, CHARLES, Ms1991-048; Founding dean of the College of Architecture and Urban Studies at Virginia Tech (1964-79). Three color snapshots of Chas. Burchard and his wife, Debbie, ca. 1990.
- CENTENNIAL COLLECTION (VPI, 1972), This collection contains mounted photographs used in a display for the 1972 VPI Centennial celebration. Photos include: chemistry classroom (1900); first five presidents of Virginia Tech; VAMC cadet band; Preston Olin building; two football players (1904); Cowgill Hall; and cadets on the drill field (1904). Unmounted copies of most of these photographs can be found in the general photograph collection under specific subjects.
- CORPS OF CADETS PHOTOGRAPHS, ca. 1927-28, Six photographs of the VPI Corps of Cadets from 1927 or 1928 in various stages of decorum. Includes photographs of the Corps marching in formation and in costume for the Rat Parade, and the condition of the barracks after Class Night.
- CROSS, WILLIAM S. JR, Class of 1941. Collections consist of photographs of the VPI campus and students in 1941. Also includes resumes and photographs of 1941 graduates in the VPI industrial engineering department.
- DALTON, JACK, Instructor in English, 1930-34. Collection contains thirty-four snapshots and three 8x10 photos of campus life and environs, 1924-25.
- DAWLEY, WILLIAM SAMUEL, Attended VPI from 1910 to 1912. Collection consists of four mounted photographs of cadets and football team, ca. 1910-12.
- DRAKE, I. N., Railroad historian. Collection includes photographs of various railroad stations in Virginia.
- GARNETT, WILLIAM ROANE, Class of 1922. Collection contains fifty-three photographs of corps activities, campus views, and 1922 commencement.
- GOODLOE, WILLIAM TAVENOR, Class of 1923. Collection consists of eight photographs of students dressed for Rat parade, Rat May Day, and Virginia Tech College Six Orchestra; all taken in 1921.
- HALE, CHARLES RAYMOND, SR.
  Folder includes copies of photographs from Hale's time working for Norfolk & Western Railroad.
- HAMMERSLEY, COL. E. HOWARD JR. (1915-1992), Native of Roanoke, Virginia, and photographer for the Roanoke Times from 1938 until his retirement in 1980. Served in the U.S. Army Air Corps from 1942 to 1945. Collection consists of 501 negatives of photographs and slides (1936-78) taken by Hammersley of Virginia Tech football games (including "Turkey Day Classics") and the Corps of Cadets, and one reel of 70mm Hulcher film of VPI football.
- HANNAS, ANNA, Superintendent of the campus Infirmary from 1906 to 1945. Collection includes: fifty-six photos of individual cadets; thirty-one photos of unidentified individuals; seventeen photos of groups; forty-nine photos of student activities including sham battles, minstrels, and corps of cadets; Blacksburg photos including Yellow Sulphur Springs Hotel, Earhart's cave on Heth property; Palmer's gate; and a flood in back of William Preston Hotel. Photographs were taken between 1906 to 1945.
- HOMES, W. A. [William Albert], Class of 1910. Collection consists of 8 mounted photographs and one unmounted strip of photographs showing cadet life c. 1906-09, including barrracks, plant, Aunt Nellie's Cave, and paddling.
- JACKSON, HASWELL, Class of 1935. Collection consists of 19 photographs of a Rat initiation parade (1931) and a football game half-time cadet drill (1937 or 1938).
- JONES, ROBERT S., Class of 1928. Collection includes fifty-seven photographs of football games, campus scenes, and rat parades, 1924-27.
- LANCASTER, LUCY LEE, Class of 1925 and librarian, 1925-1975, at Virginia Tech. This collection contains approximately forty photographs of Blacksburg and Montgomery County, Virginia, people and places. Includes photos of the construction of Montgomery Tunnels. Slides of Lancaster's various international travels can be found with her personal papers (Ms82-019).
- LESTER, DOUGLAS, Owner of Lester's Photo Shop in Christiansburg, Virginia. Collection consists of approximately 100 historical photographs of Virginia Tech, including buildings, corps of cadets, campus views, and sports. Most of the photos were taken by Henry Harris Hill in the early 1900s (Hill was a 1907 graduate of VPI and a member of the Chemistry faculty from 1907 to 1950.) Other copies of many of these images can be found in the general photograph collection under specific subjects.
- MCCOWN, ALBERT TAYLOR, VPI alumnus. Collection consists of postcards of the Blacksburg railroad station, Mountain Lake, and VPI, ca. 1940s or 1950s. VPI photos include: (old) library, McBryde Building (Machinery Hall), Barracks No. 1, stock barns, Barracks No. 1 and 2; Alumni Gate, and battalion formation.
- MALLORY, WALTER L., Class of 1908. This collection of five photographs (1908) of the corps, football teams, and VPI farm, was divided by subject into the general photograph collection.
- MASSEY, ARTHUR BALLARD, Professor of Biology, 1918-1959. Collection includes eighty photographs (1905-1950) of campus trees (with an identifying list), four photos of various campus scenes, and eight pictures of the cutting of the Mall through campus (1950).
- MILLER, EDWARD CAMPBELL, VPI Business Manager, 1922-1944. Collection contains seven photographs of campus scenes of cadets in formation and marching.
- MURRILL, ASHBY, Class of 1901. Collection contains three photographs: Shops class (1892/93), William A. Murrill, P.S. Murill.
- NORFOLK AND WESTERN RAILWAY TRAIN WRECK IN WEST VIRGINIA, 1937., Eighteen photographs with negatives of the wreck of a Norfolk and Western Railway train in Maybeury, West Virginia, in 1937.
- PARSONS, BERNARD L. (1922-1990), Professor of Agricultural Engineering from 1947 to 1985. Photographs gathered by Parsons and other members of the Agricultural Engineering faculty of cornfields, meadow strips, terraced fields, orchards, highway erosion and wildlife borders taken by the Soil Conservation Service. Also includes photographs from the 1920s of farm, farmland, farm machinery and buildings, and of the students and facilities at the Virginia Tech Agricultural Engineering Department.
- PEALE, WALTER O., Class of 1904. This collection contains seventeen small portrait shots of unidentified students (cadets), ca. 1904.
- PORTER, J. CARLTON, Class of 1934. This collection contains approximately 350 photographs of campus scenes, the corps of cadets, and sports.
- ROANOKE TIMES AND WORLD-NEWS. NEW RIVER VALLEY PHOTOGRAPHS (see also Oversize Box 1 and Oversize Box 2), Mounted photographs used for New River Valley Exhibit by Roanoke Times and World-News. Includes historical photos of Blacksburg, Montgomery County, and other place in the New River Valley.
- ROBESON, FRANK LEIGH, Class of 1904; taught Mathematics and Drawing, 1904-13; Professor of Physics, 1913-54. Collection includes thirteen photographs of Blacksburg scenes, ca. 1904.
- ROBESON, MARY MATTHEWS, Wife of Frank L. Robeson, Professor of Physics at VPI. Collection consists of thirty photographs of campus buildings and three of Main Street, Blacksburg, 1900-18.
- SAUNDERS, CARTER TEMPLE, Class of 1904. Collection includes nine photographs of cadets and football teams in the early 1900s.
- SCHOENE, WILLIAM J., Professor of Entomology, 1913-52. Collection consists of two photographs that include Schoene: first Cumberland-Shenandoah Fruit Conference (20 July 1928) and Bee Keeper's Meeting (no date).
- SLAYTON, CLARENCE H., Class of 1910. Appr. 25 negatives of groups, Virginia Tech buildings and landscapes, and individuals, ca. 1908-10.
- SMYTH, ELLISON A., Professor of Biology, 1891-1925; Dean of the faculty, 1903-06; and Dean of Department of Applied Sciences, 1916-20. Collection contains eight photographs of campus scenes and laboratory rooms, 1890s. See also Ellison A. Smyth, Jr. Papers, Ms81-098 and Ellison A. Smyth, Jr. Glass Slide Collection.
- VAWTER, CHARLES ERASTUS, Professor of Physics, 1898-1917. Collection consists of portrait shots of Vawter and other unidentified individuals.
- WALLER, JAMES AUGUSTUS, Class of 1919; Agricultural Engineer, Agricultural Extension Divsion, 1923-56; Professor of Agricultural Engineering, 1956-58. This collection of thirty-five photographs and postcards of corps and campus scenes, 1914-17, was divided by subject into the general photograph collection.
- WAUGH, DAN BLAIR, Attended VPI from 1907-10. Collection consists of photocopies of early photographs of the campus (ca. 1907-11).